We are going to review a little more this notochordal process so you now have an image
even more precise.
A sort of dome, like this, and
a dome like this.
The embryonic stalk is over here.
So the trophic source is here.
The ectodermal tissue, the one above, is already.
more polarized, more absorbent,
this becomes
a point of support.
It does this.
Except everything grows.
You can imagine everything grows.
Everything gathers around.
And it creates.
This,
it becomes
the Henson node.
At this moment,
I also have, here, at the same time, a whole area of aspiration that
below will create a space
that opens between my ecto
and my endo, between my epiblast and my endo.
This space will cause that at the level of my primitive streak, there is this
area of aspiration.
of aspiration, and the cells, which are epithelial cells,
are pulled towards
the center, you see this image, they are drawn to the center, compressing, becoming
bottle-shaped cells, moving beneath, releasing an acid, which we call
hyaluronic
acid, this will be very important later in protein structures of
structuring, but it doesn’t matter, we come underneath and start filling
the space
below, you see, and that’s...
that’s how my mesoderm will develop.
So, at the same time I have this wave,
I have an area of aspiration creating a primitive streak,
I have this movement,
there I have a movement that pulls the cells towards the center,
at the same time, my Henson node is advancing,
I am still the coolest place,
I do not move,
who am I?
3.0.
the zero point, and I am observing all this, like this,
I am the master.
At the same time, now, in this same development, there is nodal fluid
in there, okay?
Since it is in the notochord, it’s called nodal fluid, not complicated.
Why do the cells that are in the dome,
develop faster,
we found that the cells
in this process
expand,
as they are more in
an expansion area,
they multiply much faster
than those who are on the same line
but are being converged.
They develop slower.